[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
openzity is the only open source way to
embed zero trust networking into your
app giving you unprecedented control and
security
give your app superpowers using an
opencd sdk and a few lines of code
never face the horrors of vpns dns or
inbound ports
no networking engineering skills needed
openzd is trusted by developers at
microsoft oracle and ramco
if you don't want to host opencd
netfoundry can with free plans at
netfoundry.io
se radio that's n-e-t-f-o-u-n-d-r-y
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchali my guest
today is frank mcsherry and we'll be
talking about materialize frank is the
chief scientist at materialize and prior
to that he did a fair bit of relatively
public work on data flow systems first
at microsoft research silicon valley and
most recently eth zurich he also did
some work on differential privacy back
in the day frank welcome to the show
thanks very much actually i'm delighted
to be here
frank so let's get started with
materialize and set the context for the
show so can you start by describing what
is materialized
certainly so material is a great way to
think about it is it's a sql database
the same sort of thing you're used to
thinking about when you pick up postgres
or
something like that except that its
implementation has been changed to
excel really at maintaining views over
data as the data change rapidly right
traditional databases are pretty good at
holding a pile of data letting you ask a
lot of questions rapid fire edit if you
flip that around a little and say what
if i've got the same set of questions
over time and the data are really what
are changing materials does a great job
of doing that efficiently for you and
reactively so that you get told as soon
as there's a change rather than having
to sit around and pull and ask over and
over again
so something that sits on top of
streaming data i suppose is the classic
use case that's a great way to think
about it yeah i mean there's at least
two positionings here one is
okay so streaming is very broad any data
show up at all and materials absolutely
will do some stuff with that the model
in that case is that your data your your
table if you were thinking about it as a
database is full of all those events
that have showed up
and what we'll absolutely do a thing for
you in that case a place that
materializes really excels and
distinguishes itself though is when that
stream that's coming in is a change log
coming out of some transactional source
of truth so your upstream oltp style
instance which has very clear sort of
changes to the data that have to happen
atomically at very specific moments
and you know there's a lot of streaming
infrastructure that you could apply to
this to this data and maybe or maybe not
you'd actually get out exactly the
correct sql semantics from it and
materialize is really
i would say position that people who
have a database in mind like they have a
collection of data that they're thinking
of that they are changing adding to or
moving from
and they want the experience the lived
experience of
a transactionally consistent sql
database
so
in a world where you have many different
systems for data management and data
infrastructure
can you talk about the use cases that
are solved today and where materialize
fits in where does it fill the gap in
terms of
fitting into the existing data
infrastructure in an existing company
maybe start by saying what sort of
systems are present and what's lacking
and where does materialize fit in in
that ecosystem certainly so this won't
be comprehensive there's a tremendous
amount of exciting interesting bits of
data infrastructure out there but in
broad strokes you often have a durable
source of truth somewhere this is your
database is your otp instance this is
holding on to your customer data it's
holding on to the purchases they've made
and the products you have in stock and
you don't screw around with this this is
correct source of truth you could go to
that and ask all of your questions often
but these databases often aren't
designed to really survive
heavy analytic load or continual
querying to drive you know dashboards
and stuff like that
so a product that's shown up you know
20 30 years or so has been the the olap
database the online analytic processing
database which is a different take on
the same data laid out a little bit
differently to make asking questions
really efficient
so you sort of get in there and grind
over your data really quick and ask
questions like you know how many of my
sales in this particular time period had
some characteristics so that i can learn
about my business or my customers or
whatever it is that that i'm doing
and that's a pretty cool bit of
technology that also often lives in a
modern organization however they're not
usually designed to i mean they sort of
think about taking the data that is
there and reorganizing laying it out
carefully so that it's fast access and
the data are continually changing that's
a little annoying for these sorts of
systems and they're not really optimized
for freshness let's say
uh you know they can they can do
something like you know adding data in
two counts not so hard but modifying
a record that used to be the maximum
value you got to find the second biggest
one now that sort of thing is annoying
for them
now with that
people have realized like okay there are
some use cases where we'd actually like
to have really fresh results
and we don't want to have to go hit the
source of truth again and folks have
started to build streaming platforms
things like confluence kafka offerings
and viverica's flink stuff these are
systems that
are very much designed to take event
streams of some storm you know they
might just be raw data that's landing
into kafka or they might be more
meaningful
change data capture coming out of these
transactional processing databases but
pushing those through streaming systems
where to date i would say most of them
have been tools rather than products
right so they're
software libraries that you can start
coding against and
yeah if you get things right you'll get
a
result that you're pretty proud of and
produces correct answers but it's a
little bit on you
and they've started to go up the stack a
little bit to provide
fully featured products where you're
actually seeing correct answers coming
out consistently
though they're not generally there yet
and i would say materialism is trying to
fit into that slot to say like as
you have expected for transactional
databases and for analytic databases if
you're trying to think about a stream
database not just a stream programming
platform or stream processing toolkit
but a database i think that maintains
consistency maintains invariants for you
scales out horizontally and stuff like
that but all of the things you expected
database to do for you for continually
changing data is where we're
sneaking in and hoping to get everyone
to agree oh thank goodness you did this
rather than me
analytics on top of streaming data must
be a somewhat of a common use case now
that streaming data event data is so
common and pervasive in all kinds of
technology stacks
how does
someone support
answering the analytical questions that
you might support with say materialize
today without materialize yeah it's a
good question i mean i think there's a
few different takes again i don't want
to
announce that i know all of the flavors
of these things because it's
repeatedly surprising how creative and
inventive people are but generally the
ticks are you have
always at your hands various analytic
tools that you can you can try to use
and they have knobs related to freshness
and some of them like you know click
house will happily let you append data
and get it involved in your aggregates
very quickly
so if you're tracking maximum
temperatures of a bunch of sensors yeah
it's fine you know it'll be very fresh
as long as you keep adding measurements
and
you know things only go sideways in some
of the
maybe more niche cases for some people
like having to retract data or
potentially having to do more
complicated sql style joins so a lot of
these engines don't quite excel at that
i would say the olap things either
respond quickly to changes in data or
support complicated sql expressions
multi-way joins or multi-level
aggregations stuff like that
so those tools exist other than that
your data infrastructure team skills up
on something like flink or case streams
and just starts to learn how do i how do
i put these things together if you ever
need to do anything more yet more
exciting than just
dashboards that count things accounting
is pretty easy i think a lot of folks
know that they're a bunch of products
that that will handle accounting for you
but if you needed to take events that
come in look them up in a customer
database that's supposed to be
current and consistent not accidentally
ship things to the wrong address or
something like that
yeah you kind of either have to sort of
roll this your own or accept a certain
bit of stillness in your data
and
you know it depends on who you are
whether this is okay or not i think
people are realizing now that
they can move along from just counting
things or you know getting information
that's an hour still they're like really
current current things one of one of our
users is currently
using it for cart abandonment so they're
trying to sell things to people
and a person walks away from their
shopping cart like you don't want to
know that tomorrow or to me it's even an
hour you know you probably have lost the
customer at that point
and so trying to figure out like that
logic for determining
what's going on with my business i want
to know now rather than as a postmortem
people are realizing that they can do
more sophisticated things and their
appetite has increased i suppose i would
say that's part of what makes
materialize more interesting is that
people realize they can do cool things
if you give them the tools
and one way to circumvent that would be
to write your own application level
logic keep track of what's flowing
through and service the use cases that
you want to serve maybe absolutely
that's a good point this is another form
of data infrastructure which is really
totally bespoke right like put your data
somewhere and write some more
complicated
pile of microservices and application
logic that you wrote that just sort of
sniff around in all of your data and you
cross your fingers and hope that your
education in distributed systems isn't
going to cause you to show up as a
cautionary tale in consistency or
something like that
i think that makes it even harder if you
have like one-off queries that you want
to ask one time then spinning off a
service writing application level code
to serve that one off is time-consuming
maybe
not relevant by the time you actually
have that answer
so let's talk about materialize from a
user's perspective how does someone
interact with materialize what does that
look like yeah so the intent is it's
meant to be as close as possible to a
traditional sql
experience you you connect using pg wire
so it's in a sense as if we were
postgres
and really really the goal is to look as
much as sql as possible because there's
lots of tools out there that
aren't going to get rewritten for
materialize or certainly not yet and so
they're going to show up and say i
assume that you are let's say postgres
and i'm going to say things that
postgres is supposed to understand and
hope you work
so the experience is meant to be very
similar there's a few deviations and
i'll try to call those out so materials
is very excited about the idea in
addition to creating tables and
inserting things into tables and stuff
like that
you're also able to create what we call
sources which in sql end these are a lot
like foreign tables
so
this data that we don't have it on hand
at the moment we're happy to go get it
for you and process it as it starts to
arrive and materialize but we don't
actually we're not sitting on it right
now you can't insert into it or remove
from it
but it's enough of a description of the
data for us to go and find it this is
like a kafka topic or some s3 buckets or
something like that
and with that in place you're able to
then do a lot of standard stuff your
builds select from blah blah you're able
to create views and probably the most
exciting thing in materials most
differentiating thing is creating
materialized views so when you create
view you can put the materialized
modifier in front of it and that tells
us gives us permission basically to go
and build a data flow that will not only
determine those results but maintain
them for you so that any subsequent
selects from that view will essentially
just be reading out of memory they will
not redo any joins or aggregations or
any complicated work like that
in a way you're saying materialized
views are very similar to what databases
do with materialized views except that
the source data is not internal to the
database itself and some other tables on
top of which you're creating a view but
it's actually from kafka topics and
other sources so what other sources can
you ingest data into on top of which you
can
query using sql-like interface
the most common one that we've had
experience with has been pulling out in
one way or the other i'll explain a few
this changed data capture coming out of
transactional sources of truth so for
example materialize is more than happy
to connect to postgres's logical
replication log and just pull out a
postgres instance and say we're going to
replicate things up essentially simply
or a postgres replica
there's also an open source project
debisium that is attempting to
be a lot of different change data
capture for different databases writing
into kafka and we're happy to pull
dibysium
out of kafka and have that populate
various relations that we maintain and
compute
but you can also just take kafka right
like records in kafka with uh you know
with avro schemas there's an ecosystem
for this pull them into materialize and
they'll be treated you know without the
changed data capture going on they'll
just be treated as append only so each
each neuron that you get yeah it's like
as if you added that into the table that
you were or as if someone typed an
insert statement with those contents but
you don't actually have to be there
typing the insert statement we'll be
watching the stream for you
and then you can feed that into these
these sql views there's some cleverness
that goes on you might say what wait
append only that's going to be enormous
and there's definitely some cleverness
that goes on to make sure things don't
fall over
the intended experience i suppose this
very naive sequel as if you had just
populated these tables with massive
results
but behind the scenes the cleverness is
looking at your sql query and say oh we
don't we don't actually need to do that
do we we can
pull the data in aggregate it as it
arrives we can retire data once certain
things are known to be true about it but
the libya experience very much meant to
be
uh you know sql you you the user don't
need to
you know there's like one or two new
concepts mostly about expectations like
what types of queries should go fast
should go slow but the tools that you're
using
don't need to suddenly speak new
dialects of sql or anything like that
you can connect through jdbc or
something to materialize and just
consume that information i believe so
yeah the thing that i'm definitely not
expert on is all of the quirks so
someone could be listening it's like oh
no frank don't say that don't say that
it's a trick
and i want to be careful about that but
absolutely you know with the appropriate
amount of typing pg wire is the thing
100 yes and various jdbc drivers
definitely work though occasionally they
need a little bit of help you know some
modifications to explain how a thing
actually needs to happen given that we
are not literally postgresql so you said
some ways you're similar which you just
described in some ways you're different
from sql or you don't support certain
things that are supported in a
traditional database so what are those
things that are not
like a traditional database and
materialize or would you not support
from a sql perspective
yeah it's a good question so i would say
there's some things that are sort of
subtle so for example we're not very
happy to have you build a materialized
view that has non-deterministic
functions in it
i don't know if you were expecting to do
that but if you put something like rand
or now in a materialized view they're
going to tell you no
i guess i would say modern sql is
something that we're not
racing towards at the moment so we
started with sql 92 as
a lot of sub queries joins all sorts of
correlation all over the place if you
want
but are not yet match recognized and
stuff like that so this is equal to 2016
or something like that
there's a rate at which we're trying to
bring things in we're trying to do a
good job of
being confident in what we put in there
versus racing forward with features that
are
mostly baked or work fifty percent of
the time my take is that there's an
uncanny valley essentially between
not really sql systems and sql systems
and if you show up and say we're sql
compatible but actually
10 of what you might type will be
rejected this is not nearly as useful as
100 or 99.99
it's just no longer useful to pretend to
be sql compatible at that point someone
has to rewrite their tools that's what
makes uh makes a difference
the main differences are performance
related you know that
if you try to use material as an oltp
source of truth you're going to find
that it behaves a bit more like a batch
processor if you try to see what is the
peak insert throughput
sequential inserts not patch inserts the
numbers there are going to be for sure
lower than something like postgres which
is really good at getting in and out as
quickly as possible
maybe i would say our transaction
support is not as exotic as most of the
other transactions in materialize but
the set of things that you can do in a
transaction are more limited
what about something like triggers can
you support triggers based on absolutely
not absolutely not no no okay
so triggers are
a declarative way to describe imperative
behavior right another example actually
is window functions are a thing that
technically we have support for but no
one's going to be impressed
so window functions similarly are
usually used as a declarative way to
describe imperative programs like
do some grouping this way and then walk
one record at a time forward maintaining
this state and like i suppose it's
declarative but it's it's not in the
sense that anyone really intended and
they're super hard unfortunately super
hard to maintain efficiently if you want
to grab the median element out of a
collection who've
there are algorithms that you can use
that are smart to do that but getting
general sql to update incrementally is a
lot harder when you add certain
constructs that
absolutely people want for sure so
that's a bit of a challenge actually is
spending that gap
when it comes to different sources
you have cafe topics you can connect to
a change data capture stream can you
join those two things together to create
a materialized view of search from
multiple sources
absolutely i totally forgot that this is
might be a surprise absolutely of course
so what happens in materialize is these
sources of data may come with their own
views on transaction boundaries they may
have no opinions at all like the kafka
topics may have just like hey i'm i'm
just here but the postgres might have
clear transaction boundaries as they
arrive at materialize they get
translated to sort of materialize local
timestamps that respect the transaction
boundaries on the inputs
but are relatable to each other
essentially the first moment at which
materialize was aware of the existence
of
a particular record and absolutely you
can just you can join these things
together you can take
a dimension table that you maintain in
postgres and join it with a fact table
that's spilling in through kafka
and get exactly consistent answers as
much as that makes sense when you have
kafka and postgres and they're they're
coordinated but we'll be showing you an
answer that actually corresponds to a
moment in the kafka topic and a specific
moment in the postgres instance that
were roughly contemporaneous
you said correctness was an important
aspect in what you do with materialize
so if you're working with two different
streams maybe one is lagging behind
maybe it's the underlying
infrastructure is just you know
partition from your materialize instance
maybe so
does that surface the user in some way
or do you just provide an answer that's
somewhat correct and also tell the user
yeah we we don't know for sure what's
coming from the other topic that's a
great question and this is this is one
of the main pain points in stream
processing systems is this trade-off
between
availability and correctness basically
if the data are slow what do you do do
you hold back results or do you show
people sort of bogus results
the stream processing community i think
has evolved to to get that like no you
want you want correct result because
otherwise people don't know how to use
your tool properly
and materials will do the same with a
caveat
which is that like i said material
essentially re-time stamps the data that
arrive at materialize
into materialized local time so that it
is always able to provide a current
view of what it's received but it will
also surface
that relationship those bindings
essentially between
progress in the sources and timestamps
that we've assigned so we'll be able to
tell you like
that time now like as of now
what is the max offset that we've
actually peeled out of
out of kafka for some reason that isn't
what you want it to be you know you
happen to know there's a bunch more data
ready to go
or what is the max transaction id that
we pulled out of postgres
you're able to see that information
we're not entirely sure what you the
user want to do at that point though
and you might need to
do a little bit of your own logic about
like oh wait i should wait
if i want to provide end-to-end read
your rights experience for someone
putting data into kafka i might want to
wait until i actually see that offset
that i just sent wrote the message to
reflected in the output
but it's a little tricky for materialize
to know exactly what you're going to
want ahead of time so we give you the
information
but don't prescribe any behavior based
on that
i'm missing something about
understanding how materialize
understands the underlying data so
you can connect to some kafka topic
maybe that has binary streams coming
through how do you understand
what's actually present in it and how do
you
extract columns or
type information in order to create a
materialized view it's a great question
so one of the things that's helping us a
lot here is that confluent has the
compliment schema registry which is a
bit of there of the kafka ecosystem
that maintains associations between
kafka topics and avro schemas that you
should expect to be true of the binary
payloads
and we'll happily go and pull that data
that information out of the schema
registries so that you can automatically
get a nice
bunch of columns basically we'll map
avro into the
sort of sql like relational model that's
going on
they don't perfectly match unfortunately
so we have sort of a superset of avro
and postgres data models
but we'll use that information to
properly turn these things into types
that make sense to you otherwise what
you get is
essentially one column that is a binary
blob and you're more than welcome except
one for a lot of people is convert that
to text
and use the csv splitter on it to
turn into a bunch of different text
columns and now use sql's casting
abilities to take the text into dates
times so we often see a first view that
is unpack
what we received as binary as a blob of
json maybe so you just use json to pop
all these things open
and turn that into a view
that is now
sensible with respect to you know
properly typed columns and a
well-defined schema stuff like that and
then build all of your logic based off
of that view rather than off of the raw
raw source
is that happening within materialize
when you're trying to unpack the object
if you in the absence of say a schema
registry of sorts that describes the
underlying data
so what will happen is you write these
views that say okay from from binary
let me cast it to text i'm going to
treat it as json i'm going to try to
pick out the following fields
that'll be a view
when you create that view nothing
actually happens in materialize other
than we write it down we don't start
doing any work on account of that we
wait until you say something like well
you know okay select this field as a as
a key
uh join it with this other
relation i have do it do an aggregation
do some counting but we'll then turn on
materializes machinery at that point to
look at your big you know we have to go
and get you an answer now and start
maintaining something
so we'll say great gotta do these group
buys these joins which columns do
actually need
we'll push back as much of this logic as
possible to the moment just after we
pull this out of kafka
right so we just got some bytes we're
about to i mean it's not you know step
one is probably cast it to json because
you can cunningly dive into the binary
blobs to find the fields that you need
but basically we will as soon as
possible turn it into the fields that we
need throw away the fields we don't need
and then flow it into the rest of the
the data flow this is one of the tricks
for how do we not use so much memory you
know if you only need
to do a group by count on a certain
number of columns we'll just keep those
columns just the distinct values of
those columns we'll throw away all the
other differentiating stuff that you
might be wondering where is it it
evaporated to the ether still in kafka
but it's not immaterialized so yeah
we'll do that in materialize as soon as
possible when drawing the data into the
system
the underlying
computing infrastructure that you have
that supports a materialized view
if i have two materialized views that
are created on the same underlying topic
are you going to reuse that to compute
outputs of those views or is it two
separate compute pipelines for each of
the views that you have
on top of underlying data
that's a great question the thing that
we've built at the moment does allow you
to share but requires you to be explicit
about when you want the sharing and the
idea is that maybe we could build
something on top of this that
automatically rewrites your queries in
some sort of exotic way but but yeah
what happens under the covers is that
each of these materialized views that
you've expressed like hey please please
compute this for me and keep it up to
date we're going to turn into a timely
data flow it's a system underneath
and the timely data flows are sort of
interesting in their architecture that
they allow
sharing of state across data flows
so you're able to use
in particular we're going to share index
representations of these collections
across data flows so if you want to do a
join for example between your customer
relation and your orders relation by
customer id
and maybe i don't know something else
you know addresses
with customers by customer id
that customer collection indexed by
customer id can be used by both of those
data flows at the same time we only need
to maintain one copy of that that saves
a lot on memory and
compute and communication and stuff like
that we don't do this for you
automatically because
it introduces some dependencies if we do
it automatically you might shut down one
view and
not all of it really shuts down because
some of it was needed to help out
another view we didn't want to get
ourselves into that situation so
if you want to do the sharing at the
moment you need to step one create an
index on customers in that example and
then step two just issue your queries
and we'll we'll pick up that shared
index automatically at that point but
you have to have called it that ahead of
time as opposed to have us discover it
as we just walk through your queries we
haven't called it out
so you can create a materialized view
and you can create index on those
columns and then you can issue a query
that might use the index as opposed to
the base table
classic sql like optimizations on top of
the same data may be in different forms
for better access et cetera is that the
idea for creating an index yeah it's a
good point actually to be totally honest
creating materials view and creating
index are the same thing it turns out it
materialized the materialized view that
we create is an indexed representation
of the data
where if you just say create material as
view we'll pick the columns to index on
sometimes they're really good unique
keys that we can use to index on and
we'll use those and sometimes there
aren't we'll just essentially have a
pile of data that is indexed essentially
in all of the columns of your data but
it's really it's the same the same thing
that's going on it's us building a data
flow whose output is an index
representation of the collection of data
but left in a representation that is
not only a big pile of the correct data
but also arranged in a form that allows
us random access by whatever the key of
the of the index is and you're
absolutely right that's
very helpful for subsequent like if you
want to do a join using those columns as
the key amazing like we'll literally
just use that in memory asset for the
join we won't need to allocate any more
information if you want to do a select
where you ask for
some values equal to that key that'll
come back in a millisecond or something
it will literally just do random access
into that maintained arrangement and get
your answers back so it's
the same intuition as an index like why
do you build an index both so that you
have fast you yourself have fast access
to the data but also so that subsequent
queries that you do
will be more efficient you know
subsequent joins that you do can use the
index amazing
very much the same intuition material as
at the moment and i think not a concept
that a lot of the other stream
processors have yet hopefully that's
changing but i think it's a real point
of distinction between them that you can
do this upfront work in index
construction and expect to get payoff in
terms of performance and efficiency with
the rest of your sql workloads
that's great in sql sometimes you as a
user don't necessarily know what the
best access pattern is for the
underlying data right so maybe you write
a query and you say explain and it gives
you a query plan and then you realize oh
wait i can actually make do this much
better if i just create an index fund so
and so columns is that kind of feedback
available and materialized because your
data access pattern is not necessarily
data at rest right it's streaming data
so it looks different do you have that
kind of feedback that goes back to the
user saying that i should actually
create an index in order to get answers
faster or
understand why something is really slow
i can tell you what we have at the
moment and like where i'd love us to be
is 20 years in the future from now but
so at the moment you can do the explain
queries explain plans for explain
we've got like three different plans
that you can check out in terms of
the pipeline from
type checking down to optimization down
to the physical plan what we don't
really have yet i would say is a good
assistant like you know the equivalent
of clippy for dataflow plans to say like
it looks like you're using the same
arrangement five times here
maybe you should create an index we do
mirror up you know potentially
interesting but
material mirrors up a lot of its exhaust
as introspection data that you can then
look at and we will actually keep track
of how many times are you arranging
various bits of data various ways so the
interested person could go and look and
say oh that's weird i'm making four
copies of this particular index when
instead i should be using it four times
they've got some homework to do at that
point to figure out what that index is
but it's absolutely the sort of thing
that a
fully featured product would want to
have so you help me make this query
faster and have it look at your your
workload and say
ah you know we
we could take these five quiz you have
jointly optimize them and do something
better in database then this is this is
multi-query optimization is the name for
this or a name for anything like it
anyhow and
it's hard it's uh it's it's
unfortunately there's not just an easy
like oh yeah it's a solid problem just
do it this way it's subtle and and
you're never
always sure that you're doing the right
thing
i mean sometimes what material is trying
to do is to bring streaming performance
even more people
and any steps that we can take to give
it even better performance to even more
people for people who aren't nearly as
excited about diving in and
understanding how data flows work and
stuff and just had a button that says
think more and go faster
would be great i mean i'm all for that
opencd is the only open source way to
embed zero trust networking into your
app giving you unprecedented control and
security
give your app superpowers using an open
cd sdk and a few lines of code
never face the horrors of vpns dns or
inbound ports
no networking engineering skills needed
openzd is trusted by developers at
microsoft oracle and ramco
if you don't want to host opencd
netfoundry can with free plans at
netfoundry.io
se radio that's n-e-t-f-o-u-n-d-r-y
let's talk a little bit about the
correctness aspect of it because that's
one of the key
points for materialize right you write a
query and you know you're getting
correct answers or you know you're
getting consistent views now if i were
to not use materialize maybe i'm going
to use some hand written code
application level logic to look over
streaming data and compute stuff what
are the pitfalls in doing so do you have
an example where you can say that
certain things are never going to
converge to an answer i was particularly
interested in something that i read on
the website where you have never
consistent was the term that was used
when you try and solve it yourself so
can you maybe give an example for what
the pitfall is and the consistency
aspect why you get it correct there's a
pile of pitfalls absolutely i'll try to
give a few examples just just to call it
out like the highest level for those who
are technically aware there's cash
invalidation is
at the heart of all of these problems so
you you held on to some data that was
correct at one point and you're getting
ready to use it again and you're not
sure if it's still correct
and this is
in essence the thing that the core of
materialize solves for you it
invalidates all of your caches for you
to make sure that you're always seeing
consistent
and you don't have to worry about that
question when you're rolling your own
stuff like is this really actually
current for what i'm about to use it for
the thing i mean this this never
consistent thing one way to maybe think
about this is that inconsistency very
rarely composes properly so if i have
two sources of data
and they're both
running they're both like eventually
consistent let's say like they'll
eventually each get to the right answer
just not necessarily at the same time
you can get a whole bunch of really
hilarious bits of behavior that you
wouldn't have thought i at least i
didn't a priority think possible
for example you might i mean the example
i worked through before is you've got
some query where you're trying to find
the max argument you want to find the
row in some relation that has the
maximum value of something
and often the way you write this in sql
is
a view that's going to pick out or a sub
query that's going to pick up the
maximum value and then a restriction
that says all right now with that
maximum value pick out all of the rows
from my input that have exactly that
value
and what's sort of interesting here is
depending on how promptly various things
update this may produce not just not the
correct answer not just a stale
version of the answer but it might
produce nothing ever
this is going to sound silly but it's
like it's possible that your max gets
updated faster than your base table does
and that kind of makes sense the max is
a lot smaller potentially easier to
maintain than your base stable
so if the max is continually running
ahead of what you've actually updated in
your base table you're continually doing
these lookups saying like hey find me
the record that has this this max value
and it's never there
and by the time you put that record into
the base table
the max has changed you want a different
thing now
so instead of what people might have
thought they were getting which is an
eventually consistent view of
their query from eventually consistent
parts what they end up getting is a
never consistent view on account of
these weaker forms of consistency don't
compose the way that you might hope that
they would compose
and if you have multiple sources of data
then it becomes all the more challenging
to make sense of it absolutely i mean to
be totally honest and fair if you have
multiple sources of data you probably
have better managed expectations about
what consistency and correctness are you
you might not have expected things to be
correct but it's especially surprising
when you have one source of data and
just because there are two different
paths that the data take through your
query you start to get weird results
that correspond to none of the inputs
that you that you had
but yeah it's all a mess and the more
that we can do our thinking is the more
that we can do to make sure that
you the user don't spend your time
trying to debug consistency issues the
better right so we're gonna try to give
you these always consistent
views they always correspond to the
correct answer for some state of your
database that it transitioned through
and for multi-input things it'll always
correspond to
a consistent moment in each of your
inputs
you know the correct answer exactly
correct answer for that so if you see a
result that comes out of materialize it
actually happened at some point and if
it's wrong for me at least i can be
totally honest as a technologist this is
amazing because it means that debugging
is so much easier right if you see a
wrong answer something's wrong you gotta
go fix it whereas in modern data or you
see a wrong answer you're like well
let's let's give it five minutes
you never really know if it's just late
or if like there is actually a bug that
is costing you money or time or
something like that i think that becomes
especially hard when you're looking at
one-off queries to make sure that what
you've written with application code for
example is going to be correct and
consistent
as opposed to relying on a database or a
system like this where there are certain
correctness guarantees that you can rely
on based on what you ask
so a lot of people reach for stream
processing systems because they want to
react quickly right like like oh yeah we
need to have low latency because we need
to do something
something important has to happen
promptly
but when you have an eventually
consistent system it comes back and it
tells you like all right i got the
answer for you it's seven
oh that's amazing seven like i should go
sell all my stock now or some i don't
know what it is and you say like you
sure at seven well you know it's seven
right now it might change in a minute
wait hold on no no
so what is the actual time to confident
action
is a question that you you could often
ask about the streaming system they'll
give you an answer real quick like it's
super easy to write a eventually
consistent system with low latency you
just say zero and then when you get the
right answer you tell them what the
right answer was and you're like yeah
well sorry i said zero first and you
know that i was a liar so like you
should have waited
but actually getting the user to the
moment where they can confidently
transact they can take whatever action
they need to do whether that's like
charge someone's credit card or send
them an email or or something like that
you can't quite as easily take back or
you know it's expensive to do so
it's a big difference between these
strongly consistent systems and the only
eventually consistent systems
yeah and for sure like the
ease of use with which you can declare
it is for me certainly seems like a huge
plus
as a system what does materialize look
like how do you deploy it well is that a
single binary can you describe what that
is
there's two different directions that
things go through there is a single
binder that you can grab materializes
source available you can go grab it and
use it it's built on open source timely
data flow differential data flow stuff
and you can you know very common way to
try this out is you grab it put it on
your laptop it's one binary it doesn't
require a stack of associated
distributed systems uh things in place
to run
you know if you want to read out of
kafka you have to have kafka running
somewhere but but you can just turn on
materialize with a single binary
p sql into it so shell into it using
your favorite pdwire interface and just
start doing stuff at that point if you
like so if you just want to try it out
read some local files or do some inserts
i don't play around with it like that
the direction that we're headed though
to be totally honest is more of this
this cloud-based setting a lot of people
are very excited about not having to
manage this on their own especially
given that a single binary is neat but
what folks actually want is a bit more
of an elastic compute fabric and an
elastic storage fabric underneath all of
this and there are limitations to how
far do you get with just one binary the
compute scales pretty well to be totally
candid but it has limits and and people
appreciate that like yes well if you
know if i have several terabytes of data
you're telling me you could put this on
memory i'm gonna need a few more
computers
so bringing people to a product that
where we can switch the implementation
in the background and turn on 16
machines instead of just one is a bit
more of where energy is at the moment
though we're really committed to keeping
the single binary experience so that you
can grab material and see what it's like
it's both helpful and useful for people
you know within license to do whatever
you want with that helpful for for
people but it's also just a good
business i suppose like you know you get
people interested like this is amazing
i'd like more of it absolutely if you
want more of it we'll set you up with
that but we want people to be delighted
with the single machine
version as well
yeah that makes sense i mean i don't
want to spin up 100 machines to just try
something out
just experiment and play with it but on
the other hand you mentioned about
scaling compute but when you're
operating on streaming data you could
have millions of billions of events that
are flowing through different topics so
depending on the view that you write
what is the storage footprint that you
have to maintain do you have to maintain
a copy of everything that has
happened and keep track of it like data
warehouse maybe you know aggregate it
and keep some form that you can use to
sell queries or
i get the sense that this is all done on
the fly when you ask for the first time
so what sort of data do you have to like
hold on to in comparison to the
underlying topic on the fly when you ask
for the first time so what sort of data
do you have to like hold on to in
comparison to the underlying topic or
other sources of data that you connect
to the answer to this is very slowly
depends on
the word you use which is what you have
to do and i can tell you the answer to
both what we have to do and what we
happen to do at the moment so at the
moment early days of materialize the
intent was very much
let's let people bring their own source
of truth so you've got your data in
kafka you're going to be annoyed if the
first thing we do is make a second copy
of your data and keep it for you
so if your data are in kafka and you've
got some key based compaction going on
we're more than happy to just leave it
in kafka for you like not make a second
copy of that pull the data back in the
second time you want to use it
so if you have three different queries
and then you come up with a fourth one
that you want to turn on the same data
we'll pull the data again from kafka for
you
and this is
meant to be friendly to people who don't
want to pay lots and lots of money for
additional copies of kafka topics and
stuff like that we're definitely moving
into the direction of bringing some of
our own persistence into play as well
for a few reasons one of them is
sometimes yeah you have to do more than
just reread someone's kafka topic if
it's an append only topic and there's no
compaction going on we need to tighten
up the representation there there's also
like when people sit down they type
insert into tables and materialize they
expect those things to be there when
they restart so we need to have a
persistent story for that as well
the main thing though that drives what
we have to do is how quickly can we get
someone to agree that they
will always do certain transformations
to their data
right so if they create a table and just
say hey it's a table we've got to write
everything down because we don't know if
the next thing they're going to do is
select star from that table
bad luck in that case
what we'd like to get at is it's a
little awkward in sql unfortunately what
we'd like to get at is allowing people
to specify sources and then
transformations on top of those sources
where they promise hey you know i don't
need to see the raw data anymore
i only want to look at the result of the
transformation so like the classic one
is i've got some appended only data but
i only want to see the last hour's worth
of records so feel free to retire data
more than an hour old
it's a little tricky to express this in
sql at the moment to express the fact
that you should not be able to look at
the original source of data like as soon
as you create it as a foreign table it's
there and someone can select star from
it and if you know if we want to give
them the right experience well it
requires a bit more cunning to figure
out what should we persist and what
should we default back to rereading the
data from it's it's sort of an active
area i would say for us figuring out how
little can we scribble down
automatically without explicit hints
from you or without having you
explicitly materialize you so you can
sorry i didn't say but in materials you
can sync out your results out to
external storage as well
and of course you can always write views
that say like
here's the summary of what i need to
know let me write that back out and i'll
read that into another view and actually
do my downstream
analytics off of that more compact
reputation so that on restart i can come
back up from that compact view you can
do a bunch of these things manually on
your own but that's a bit more painful
and we'd love to
make that a bit more smooth and elegant
for you automatically
when it comes to the retention of data
suppose you have two different sources
of data where one of them has data going
as far back as 30 days another has data
going as far back as two hours
and you're trying to write some query
that joins these two
sources of data together can you
make sense of that do you know that you
only have at most two hours worth of
data that's actually correct and
consistent and you have extra data that
you can't really make sense of because
you're trying to join those two sources
so we can let me contrast this i guess
with what other systems might currently
have you do so a lot of other systems
you must explicitly construct a window
of data that you want to look at so
maybe two hours wide or something or
like one hour one because you know it
goes back two hours and then when you
join things life is complicated if the
two data sets don't have the same
windowing properties so if they're
different widths okay classic one is
you've got some facts fact table coming
in of
things that happened and you want to
window that because that's you don't
really care about sales from 10 years
ago
but your customer relation that's not
that window you don't delete customers
after an hour right they've been around
as long as they've been around for
you'll have to join those two things
together
material is super happy to do this for
you we do not oblige you to
put windows
into your query windows are essentially
a change data capture pattern right like
if you want to have a one hour wide
window on your data after you put every
record in one hour later you should
delete it that's just a change the data
undergoes it's totally fine and with
that view on things you can take a
collection of data that
is only one hour you know every one hour
after any record gets introduced it gets
retracted
and join that with
a pile of data that's never having
rejected or is experiencing different
changes like only when a customer
updates their their information does
that data change and these
just two collections that change and
there's always a corresponding correct
answer for when you go into a join and
try to figure out where should we ship
this package to
yeah you don't miss the fact that the
customer's address has been the same for
the past month
and they fell out of the window or
something like that that's crazy no one
wants that
definitely don't want that kind of
complexity showing up in how you write
your sequel to
let's talk a little bit about data
governance aspect it's a big topic you
have lots of regions that have different
rules about data rights that the
consumer might have so i can exercise my
right to say i just want to be forgotten
i want to delete
all traces of data so
your data might be in kafka now you have
materialized it's kind of taking
that data and then transforming it into
aggregates or other information
how do you handle this sort of
governance aspect when it comes to data
deletions maybe or just audits and
things like that to be totally clear we
don't solve any of these problems for
anyone this is a serious sort of thing
that using materials does not magically
absolve you of any of your
responsibilities or anything like that
though i would say materials is nicely
positioned to do something well here for
two reasons one of them is because it's
a
declarative e system with with sql
behind it and stuff like this as opposed
to a hand rolled application code or
tools
oh we're in a really good position to
look at the dependencies between phrase
bits of data if you want to know where
did this data come from was this an
inappropriate use of
certain data that type of thing
the information is i think very clear
there there's really good debug ability
why did i see this record it's not free
but it's not too hard to reason back and
say great let's write the sql query that
figures out which records contributed to
this this particular output
and macho is it specifically itself also
does a really nice thing which is
because we are giving you always correct
answers as soon as you retract an input
like if you go into your your profile
somewhere and you update something or
you delete yourself or you click you
know hide from marketing or something
like that as soon as that information
lands and materialize the correct answer
has changed and we will absolutely like
no joke update the correct answer to be
as if
whatever your current settings are or
how was at the beginning
and this is very different like a lot of
people sorry i moonlight as a privacy
person or in a past life i suppose
and there's a lot of really interesting
governance problems there because a lot
of machine learning models for example
do a great job of just
you know remembering your data and like
you deleted it but they remember
you were a great training example and so
they they basically wrote down your data
it's tricky in some of these
applications to figure out like am i
really gone are there ghosts of my data
that are still sort of echoing there and
materialize is very clear about this as
soon as the data change the output
answers change
there's a little bit more work to do to
like are you actually purged from
various logs various in-memory
structures stuff like that but in terms
of are you now serving up answers to
users that still reflect invalid data
the answer is going to be no which is a
really nice property again of strong
consistency
let's talk a little bit about the
durability you mentioned it's currently
like a single system kind of deployment
so what does recovery look like if you
were to
nuke the machine and restart
and you have a couple of materialized
views how do you recover that do you
have to recompute
generally you're going to have to
recompute we've got some sort of in
progress work on reducing this so on
capturing source data as they come in
and keeping it in more compact
representations but absolutely like at
the moment in a single binary experience
if you
read in if you honestly read in a
terabyte of data from kafka and then you
turn everything off turn it on again
you're going to read a terabyte of data
and again you can do it doing less work
in the sense that
when you read that data back in you no
longer care about the historical
distinctions so you might have let's say
you're watching your terabyte for a
month lots of things changed you did a
lot of work of the time if you read it
in at the end of the month
a material is at least bright enough to
say
all right all of the changes that this
data reflect they're all happening at
the same time so if any of them happen
to cancel we'll just get you know get
rid of them there's some other knobs
that you can play with too i mean these
are these are more of pressure release
valves than they are anything else but
any of these sources you can say like
start at kafka offset such and such you
know we've got folks who know that
they're going to do a one hour window so
they just
recreate the source saying start from
two hours ago
and even if they have a terabyte going
back in time we'll figure out the right
offset that corresponds to the timestamp
from two hours ago and and start each of
the kafka readers
at the right points
that required a little bit of a help
from the user to say it is okay to not
reread the data because of something
that they know to be true about it
can you replicate data from materialize
what you actually build into another
system
or push that out to upstream systems in
a different way
yeah
hopefully i don't speak about exactly
what we can do at the moment but all of
the materialized views that we produce
and the sinks that we write to are
getting very clear instructions about
the the changes the data undergo
like we can output back into the museum
format for example that could then be
presented at
someone else who who's prepared to go
and consume that and in principle in
some cases we can put these out with
these nice strongly consistent
timestamps so that you could pull it in
somewhere else and get
basically keep keep this chain of
consistency going where your downstream
system
responds to these nice atomic
transitions that correspond exactly to
input data transitions as well so we
definitely can it's i gotta say like a
lot of the work that goes on in
something like materialize
the computer infrastructure has sort of
been there from early days but there's a
lot of adapters and stuff to write like
a lot of people are like oh you know i'm
using a different format or i'm using
you know can you do this
in ork instead of parquet or
can you push it out to google pub sub or
azure event hubs this is like an
unlimited number of
yes with a little caveat of like this is
the list of actually support options
yeah or just write your own adapter kind
of a thing and then you can connect to
whatever yeah a great way if you want to
write your own thing material is it just
when you're logged into p sql connection
you can tail any view in the system and
that will give you a first day snapshot
at a particular time and then a strongly
consistent change stream from that
snapshot going forward and your
application logic can just like oh
amazing i'll do whatever i need to do
with this commit it to a database
but this is you writing a little bit of
code to do it but we're more than happy
to help you out with that in that sense
let's talk about some other use cases do
you support something like
tailing the log and then trying to
extract certain things and then building
a query out of it
which is not very easy to do right now
but can i just point you to a file that
you might be able to ingest as long as i
can also describe what format of the
lines are or something like that
yes for a file absolutely do i should
check to see what we support in terms
like log rotation like that's
the harder problem is so if you point us
at a file we will keep reading the file
and every time we get notified that its
length has changed we'll go back and
read some more the idiom that a lot of
people use sort of more devops is you've
got a place that the logs are going to
go and you make sure to cut the logs
every whatever happens hour day
something like that and
rotate them so that you're not building
one massive file and at that point i
don't know that we actually have i
should check built-in support for like
sniffing a directory and sort of
watching for the arrival of new files
that we then
seal the file we're currently reading
and pivot over and stuff like that so
it's all
it seems like a very tasteful and not
fundamentally challenging thing to do
really all the work goes into the bit of
logic that is
what do i know about you know the
operating system and what your plans are
for the logger rotation you know all of
the rest of the
compute infrastructure
the sql the the timely data flow the
incremental view maintenance all that
sort so that stays the same
so it's more a matter of getting some
folks who are savvy with these patterns
to sit down
type some code for a week or two to
figure out how do i you know how do i
watch for new files in a directory and
what's the idiom for naming that i
should use
i guess you could always go about very
roundabout way to just push that into a
kafka topic and then consume it off of
that and then you get a continuous
stream and you don't care about where
the source is for the topic yeah there's
a lot of things that you definitely
could do and like i have to restrain
myself every time because i i would say
something like it's like oh you could
just push on the cop and then
immediately everyone says no you can't
do that you know here's the really
important reason
and i i don't want to be too casual but
but you're absolutely right like if you
have the information there
you could also
have just a relatively small script that
takes that information like watches it
itself and inserts that using a p sql
connection into materialize and then
i'll go into our own persistence
representation which is good and bad
depending on
maybe you were just hoping those files
would be the only thing but at least it
works we've seen a lot of really cool
use cases that people have shown up and
been more creative than i've been for
sure like they've put together a thing
you're like oh that's not going to work
oh what it works wait how did you and
then they explained you know oh you know
i just have someone watching here and
i'm writing to a
fifo here and i'm very impressed by the
creativity and new things that people
can do with materialize it's cool seeing
that with a tool that sort of opens up
so many different
new modes of working with data
yeah it's always nice to build systems
that you can compose other systems with
to
get what you want i want to touch on
performance for a bit so
compared to
writing some applications i will code
maybe to
figure out data maybe it's not correct
but you know you write something to
give you the output that is an aggregate
that's grouped by something
versus doing the same thing on
materialize
what are the trade-offs do you have like
performance trade-offs because of the
correctness aspects that you guarantee
do you have any comments on that yeah
there's definitely a bunch of trade-offs
of different flavors so let me point out
a few of the good things first i'll see
if i can remember any bad things
afterwards so because the queries get
expressed a sequel they're generally
data parallel which means material is
going to be pretty good at purchasing
the workout across multiple worker
threads potentially machines if you're
using those those options and so your
query which you might have just thought
of is like okay i'm going to do a group
by account you know we will do the same
things of sharding the data out there
doing pre-aggregation shuffling it and
taking as much advantage as we can of
all of the cores that you've you've
given us
the underlying dataflow system has the
performance-wise the appealing property
that
it's very clear internally about
when do things change and when are we
certain that things have not changed
and it's all event-based so that you
learn as soon as the system knows that
an answer is correct you don't have to
to roll that by hand or do some polling
or any other funny business that's the
thing that's often very tricky to get
right if you're going to sit down and
just hand draw some code people often
like i'll gem it in the database and
i'll
ask the database every so often the
trade-offs in the other direction to be
honest are mostly like if you happen to
know something about your use case or
your data that we don't know
it's
often going to be a little better for
you to implement things so an example
that was true in early days of
materialize we've since fixed it is if
you happen to know that
you're maintaining a monotonic aggregate
something like max that only goes up the
more data you see
you don't need to worry about keeping a
full collection of data around
materialize if it is early as if it was
keeping a max
worries about the fact that you might
delete all the data except for one
record and we need to find that one
record for you because that's the
correct answer now
we've since gotten smarter and have
different implementations when we can
prove that a stream is append only and
we'll use the different implementations
but like that type of thing it's another
example if you want to maintain the
median
incrementally there's a cute really easy
way to do this in an algorithm that
we're never going we're not going to get
there it's it's you know you maintain
two priority queues and you're
continually rebalancing them and it's
it's a cute
programming challenge type of type of
question but we're not gonna do the
story automatically so if you need to
maintain the median or some other decile
or something like that
rolling that yourself is almost
certainly going to be a lot better
i want to start wrapping things up with
one last question
where is materialized going what's in
the near future of our future what you
see for the product and users
yeah so this is a really easy answer
fortunately because i'm
with several other engineers at
materials typing furiously at it right
now so the work that we're doing now is
transitioning from the single binary to
the cloud-based solution that has an
arbitrary scalable storage and compute
backplane so that folks can
still having the experience of a single
instance that they're sitting in and
looking around spin up essentially
arbitrarily many resources to maintain
their views for them so they're not
contending for resources
i mean they have to worry about the
resources they're going to use because
they cost money but they don't have to
worry about the computer saying no you
know i can't do that and the intended
experience again is to have folks show
up and have the appearance or the feel
of an arbitrarily scalable version of
materialize that
you know as i like cost a bit more if
you try to ingest
more data or do more compute but this is
often like
people yeah absolutely i intend to pay
you for access to these features i don't
want you to tell me no is the main thing
that folks ask for and that's sort of
the direction that we're heading is is
in this re-architecting
to make sure that there is this
i would say enterprise friendly but but
essentially like use case expansion
friendly you know as you think of more
cool things to do with materialize we
absolutely want you to be able to use
them use materials for them
yeah that's super exciting well with
that i'd like to wrap up frank thank you
so much for coming on the show and
talking about materialize it's my
pleasure i appreciate you having me it's
been really cool getting thoughtful
questions that really start to tease out
some of the important distinctions
between these things
yeah thanks again this is akshay
munchale for software engineering radio
thank you for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening